In this lecture we're going
to talk about data partitioning in multi
hybrid cloud architectures.
Why first off
why do we look at data partitioning
and why it matters in multi hybrid
cloud data.
The mentioned data is cold data
is the new oil whatever the case may be.
Data costs money
especially when you start dealing
with public cloud
and specifically around egress costs.
So just throwing everything up
into a big cloud or having everything
moved from the edge into
the cloud is not necessarily reasonable.
In a lot of new edge architectures,
especially as the edge
becomes more and more capable.
So you've got to come up with a strategy
on what you're going to do with your data.
This also increases
not just the scalability, but fault
tolerance and resilience
as, clouds, as we've learned, recently,
the public clouds are not 100%
bulletproof.
They do go down
and you want your whole business
going down
because cloud service has gone down.
So you need fault tolerance.
There might be regulatory and compliance
and data sovereignty issues.
And you also want to find out the
the most cost
effective way
of utilizing of these resources.
So partitioning is a way to do this.
It means you may have multiple
copies of the same data.
But that's okay.
It turns out it's,
it turns out to be cheaper
and, builds up
some of that resilience that you need.
Okay. So what is partitioning?
It's really simple.
I take really large data
sets or groups of data sets.
And I, shard them
or break them into partitions
that are managed independently
of each other instead of manages
one big pool by the benefit of this.
Most of this benefit came out of, grid
computing in the early 2000.
Where you take big, huge data sets,
you break them up into smaller segments,
and then you distribute those across
a thousand nodes or 10,000 nodes,
and you can massively parallel,
process these things.
That's where the concepts came from.
But we see some benefits in cloud
computing itself.
So taking data, breaking it up
and then working on the individual pieces
independently and then bringing the
data back together as needed.
Okay.
There's 2 or 3.
There's but these are
the main, strategies out there.
Horizontal partitioning,
also known as sharding.
This is where I split data.
If I were to do like rows and columns,
it'd be like,
splitting data by rows.
So I've got the whole data set,
but I've only got,
I've got all the fields for the data,
but only one record
that I'm going to process.
Now that's a pretty common
way of doing things.
Pretty easy to do.
There's lots of ways to do horizontal
partitioning by region, customer
ID there's a whole bunch of different
things that you can do in that way.
Vertical partitioning.
This is where I divide
things up by the fields themselves.
And there are some use cases
that this becomes actually very powerful
if I'm processing a certain amount of data
that is highly analytical.
And those fields are,
you know, numbers that I need to run data
analytics on.
That would be a great thing
to group those together
and put those in a vertical partition
with maybe only, only a reference number
to the rest of the data.
That is in the other columns inside,
your, your virtual, spreadsheet
that you have there or if you're using
a database, same, same concept.
The last one is directory
based partitioning.
This is great for file
system, types of things.
And this gives you the ability
to group things
any way that you want
in these different directories.
And then the,
the directories, can become their own
partitions that I can distribute
across, a vast, ecosystem of clouds
if I want different regions or private
clouds, public clouds, or the edge.
So you've got to come up with a strategy,
that you want to use.
These are just three main strategies
that we see a lot.
Right.
But you may have something else
that, you do, but writing down
what your partitioning strategy
is is the most important thing
when you start building
out your data strategies.
Okay.
So great
example here you can see a directory
I've got several partitions here.
And then also if I've got a table
horizontal and vertical partitioning work
really well.
Once you have a graph database I could do
the same thing with the graph database.
And it if it's more like a directory
service type of thing,
I can take the top of a graph and say,
oh, that's its own partition.
I'm going to partition
that off in a certain,
region or cloud or edge or whatever
you want to do,
come up with your own strategy
and then document it.
That's key.
Document what your strategy is
so that you can follow it.
So you've got a guideline.
And then you can follow.
Okay.
Placement of data.
Now that you've figured out
your partitions.
Now let's talk about
where am I going to put these partitions.
Now you could replicate partitions
to increase high availability.
But you need to come up with where
am I going to distribute these partitions.
And remember
there's lots of different locations
the edge private cloud, public cloud,
right
data centers, workstations, things like
you've got to determine
where you're going to do them
and then look at where
you're placing things.
There's key criteria
that you should look at.
Latency,
compliance cost and your workload itself.
Right.
It does not make sense to partition
your data that needs like an I
and, maybe your training data,
and you're going to run that on an edge
that doesn't have a GPU.
That just doesn't make sense, right?
If I'm doing training,
but if I'm doing inference,
I then maybe I can put that on the edge,
right?
That data can go out on the edge. Right.
Because I don't need a GPU
for that sort of thing.
So understanding your workload,
the resources
that are available
in each of the locales is also important.
All right.
Some of the challenges
now, we've seen this before,
and there's actually some really cool
architectures out there
and some products that fit in this space
that handle a lot of the challenges
of the multi hybrid cloud data
partitioning problem around latency or,
inter cloud bandwidth,
balancing all this stuff.
There's some great architectures
that you can look at that are out there.
Macromedia has a product out there.
Hammer space does something like this.
NetApp does stuff like this.
So you can look at that.
That's at the real data
and storage, tier.
If you want to make your stuff
more intelligent, you can look at
your application stack more
and make these, partitioning decisions,
which can overcome a lot of,
the complexity that you have in there.
But realize that your data is now
segregated, separated.
You created some silos. There.
You're going to have to understand
if I'm, combining data
or moving data between things,
that's going to have a play here
that you need to watch out for.
Also, make sure that you handle security
between the partitions
if you have to move data
between locations, or
if you're moving data between partitions,
make sure that you've established
what your governance and trust
boundaries are across those things.
All right.
Some of the best practices are align
partition
partition keys
to natural application usage.
This is a huge one.
And I see people make this mistake a lot
where maybe they partition
their data based off of region,
which is amount of you.
It sounds like a good idea,
but if their applications,
if it requires all their applications
to run in every single region,
how might not be necessarily
the best way to go, especially
if all the data is not required
in all the regions.
Right?
Or if
if all the applications aren't required
for all the data in a region,
that just doesn't make sense.
So look at your application usage.
Look at your, legality.
Right? For, where can the data reside?
Those are important things.
Look at automating your routing
and query management.
And this is where these tools
come into play.
Or you can develop your own there right.
Make sure that you're leveraging
any cloud native partitioning
and replication features
that already exist so that you can
have that more high availability
that you're looking for.
And as we've always talked about
in all the lectures, observability
monitoring, these are like applications.
Right.
So you've got to monitor them,
make sure you're not running out of space.
Make sure that you have connectivity,
so that you can keep your whole system up
and running.
There's nothing worse
than, hey, all my machines are running,
but my storage is down.
That's, that's a disaster
waiting to happen, right?
So make sure that you tie
these data partitions and where
they're located into your disaster
recovery and backup plans.
Your partition backup plans.
Okay.
Observability.
Can't talk enough about it.
Make sure that you do have observability
built in, and your logging is built in
on your partitions, so you can know what's
going on on those partitions, how often
they're being used, their uptime,
how much space you have left.
Maybe you're going to run out of space,
whatever the case may be.
So that you can also look at the load
that's going to IO going in
and out of those, because maybe
your partitions are poorly partitioned.
You're going to find that out real quickly
by looking at your observability,
okay?
Autoscaling becomes a key aspect of this,
especially if you got one region
where you've got partitions running
that is getting clobbered.
For some reason, this tends to happen
especially around, Thanksgiving time
and the big shopping season
where a region is getting clobbered
and then it shifts to another region
as, the world wakes up
and does their shopping,
which is which is really fascinating.
You can actually see,
how many people are hitting
different regions based off of,
the monitoring that's going on.
Oh, you could say, oh, Asia is waking up.
They're starting to buy or whatever
the case may be.
Okay, so use intelligent load balancing
so I can scale up and scale down
and maybe even reroute if I'm
getting overwhelmed in the US region.
And I've got spare cycles in Asia PAC,
maybe I maybe I'll take the latency hit
because it's going to be less
than, than the load
that I'm running, on my, U.S system.
So be smart about these things,
so that you can take advantage of,
you know, all your,
resources that you have,
right?
Also take advantage of things
that are built in
automatically into some of the middleware,
like Kubernetes.
Auto scaling and, making sure that you,
have the partition aware metrics
that are built
into the autoscaling.
Okay.
Here's a great example of a multi-cloud,
hybrid cloud, architecture where
I've got three regions, I've got a, East,
a Europe West and an Asia South region.
So as I mentioned before,
depending on the load
and it could be the time of day
in that region,
the load could go up and come down.
So your autoscaler needs to be able
to take advantage of that.
But in addition
you might want to say, well, I'm okay
if I'm going to take and reroute
some of my request
instead of just being so region based
if I'm allowed.
Right, based off of,
you know, regulatory criteria,
I can leverage some of the resources
in the other regions to help me out.
So be smart about this
and come up with a good strategy.
Remember, we've talked about
in the observability lecture
about, establishing your sla's,
your slides, your SLOs.
Make sure you have those so that you know,
when you're going to scale
and maybe when you're going to flip over
to a new partition in a new region.
Security.
I can't emphasize security enough.
We've seen way too many,
ransomware attacks and hacks,
especially around this time of year.
It tends to go up
because this is the time of year
that a lot of people, close
a lot of business.
All right?
And, emotions are high
and things like that.
So make sure
that you're looking at security.
Some key aspects on security
here is make sure that you have your arbok
your access control
all set up appropriately across
all of your regions
so that you don't get stuck.
Right.
In the middle of updating your access.
Right?
When something goes wrong,
make sure that you are using secret
management and credentials
for encryption keys,
and they should be per partition.
Don't have one encryption
key across all your partitions ten.
That tends to be a bad practice
because if they get into one,
that means they now have access
to all the other ones.
Make sure that you are encrypting
all your data at rest and in transit.
And if it's highly secure stuff,
there's new techniques out there
to even encrypt code in use, right?
In using things like confidential
computing or trusted execution
environment, concepts that are out there.
Also make sure that you're
isolating your,
partition communications
with network segmentation.
A lot of architectures
set up a data centric network
with its own keys,
and it could be an overlay network.
Try and run it off of different
Nic cards or virtual NICs if you can.
That will segregate, the data
from the application, network traffic.
Right.
And typically,
if you're moving a lot of data,
you can be more smart
about about that on those networks
and they can be optimized for that,
data transfer across those.
Make sure that you keep your audit logs
and track access across the different,
partitions and any modifications
to partition security.
All right.
In summary, data partitioning enables
scalability.
Excuse me, resilience and compliance
across, multi hybrid cloud systems.
Really beneficial
when you're looking at large systems
and and systems
that require, you know, some, resiliency
and if you've got data
that needs to be backed up,
make sure that you're backing up
all of these,
all these different partitions.
You can't just backup one, right.
Make sure that you have proper management
across the whole thing.
All right.
A great picture of, multi hybrid cloud,
including an on prem data center.
I've got different partitions,
I've got observability,
security layer autoscaling built in.
And you should have those three things
in every single region that you have,
whether it's in the private
cloud or in a public cloud.